This video is sponsored by
本期视频由Audible
Audible
赞助播出
It's no secret that when someone messes with our culture
总所周知，每当有人拿中国文化乱搞
Chinese people can get a bit..
中国人的反应都比较……
"What a load of bullsh#t"
“真尼玛不要脸”
...Defensive
...激烈
Look, man, it was broken before
毕竟受过苦日子
Handle with care, okay?
才懂珍惜当下，对吧
We may look back at them as cinematic classics today
虽然今天看是经典
But back when A Chinese Odyssey and Flirting Scholar came out
但是《大话西游》和《唐伯虎点秋香》上映之初
Stephen Chow's unorthodox take of Chinese mythology and history
周星驰的无厘头作品
Was wildly controversial
引起过不少争议
"Only you..."
“翁里鱿......”
Many saw them as undignified
很多人觉得这样很丢脸
How can you take something so full of history
这些充满文化历史的故事
And turn it into something so...
怎么可以恶搞成……
Juvenile?
这样？
While the goalpost has shifted
如今，大家接受度比较高了
Similar sentiments have never left the Chinese discourse
但类似的话题从未结束
"Sun Wokong is asexual"
“孙悟空是无性人”
This is the environment in which New Gods: Nezha Reborn was made
《新神榜：哪吒重生》就是在这种环境下横空出世
It has everything against it
一不小心就会招骂
Based on Investiture of the Gods
改编自《封神演义》
One of the most overused Chinese stories in recent years
也是近年来被改变得最多的故事之一了
This movie drastically reinterprets its source materials
但《哪吒重生》的诠释可谓极其大胆
Turning it into a... quote-unquote "Eastpunk" action anime
画风号称“东方朋克”，动作场面堪比日本动画大作
And somehow
如此大改
This visual design was widely praised
国内观众却纷纷给出好评
Dafuk happened?
咋回事呢？
It reminds me of another semi-recent film based on the same story
这就让我想起近期另一部《封神》作品
No, not that one
不不不，不是这一部
This one
是这个
League of Gods also drastically reinterprets the story
《封神传奇》也大胆改编了《封神》的故事
Giving it a shiny gold paint job
画面金逼飞蝗（非错字）
Probably hoping to blind you with the shine
务求闪瞎你的狗眼
So you don't recognize its true color:
免得你发现电影真相：
A piece of sh#t
shi片一部
You don't have to be Chinese to recognize that
就算不是中国人也能看出来
This movie doesn't feel Chinese at all
这部电影真是一点都不中国
So that begs the question
那问题来了
What makes this work
为什么这样改编可以
And not this?
这样改编就挨骂？
[Nezha Reborn: A Chinese Steampunk Mythological Anime!?]
[《哪吒重生》：中国蒸汽朋克神话动漫！？]
[Chapter One]
[第一章]
First, some background info
先说说背景故事
Investiture of the Gods is a 16th-century Chinese novel
《封神榜》是一部16世纪中国小说
About an epic war some 3000 years ago
讲述了约3000年前商朝灭亡的战争故事
Back when Queen Elizabeth was merely a middle-aged woman
当时伊丽莎白女王还只是一个中年大妈
The book tells the rise of a number of heroes
书中讲述了众多中国神话英雄的故事
One of which is Nezha
其中之一便是哪吒
A rebellious child born with immense power
一个天生叛逆、神力过人
And a strong sense of justice
有强烈正义感的孩子
As with most Chinese myths
与大多数中国神话一样
Nezha's origin story varies
哪吒的故事有多种说法
For this video, we'll stick to the 1979 animated classic
本期视频，我们以1979年经典动画《哪吒闹海》为主
In the story, the East Sea Dragon King has been terrorizing
故事中，东海龙王为祸人间
The city of Chentang Pass
陈塘关百姓苦不堪言
Brought drought to the land
长年不雨导致旱灾
And kidnaps children to his palace to eat
龙王还喜好吃男童女童
What an assh#le
真是一条龙渣
Being a hero
作为英雄
Nezha beats the living snot out of the King's henchmen
哪吒把龙王的手下打到老母都不认得
Slays the Dragon Prince who came to seek revenge
杀掉了前来报仇的龙王三太子
And trashes the King's underwater palace
并大闹龙宫，掀翻龙王家
While Nezha sees this as helping the innocents
在哪吒眼里，这是锄强扶弱
The gods, and even his own father
神仙们，还有哪吒自己的父亲
See this as a violent child defying the natural order
却觉得这是一个叛逆孩子在逆天而行
So, in one last act of defiance
受封建父权所压迫
And to appease the corrupted gods
在众神逼迫之下
Nezha ends his own life
哪吒自刎
Thus inspiring a Bruce Lee movie many centuries later
故事壮烈，数百年后李小龙也要模仿
"I didn't have much education"
“我读书少”
"Don't try to fool me"
“你不要骗我”
Don't worry, Nezha gets resurrected
别担心，哪吒几下就复活了
Nezha's story can be understood as a criticism of the feudal system
哪吒的故事可以理解为对封建制度的批判
A battle between innate morality
是先天道德
And the reality that the ruling class gets to make the law
和统治阶级制定的法律之间的冲突
It is a timeless allegory
这是一个永不过时的寓言
Which is why Nezha Reborn explores the same theme
于是，《哪吒重生》也沿用了这个主题
But from an updated perspective
只是探索的角度有所改变
In Nezha Reborn
《重生》里
Nezha is now a smuggler, living in a slum city
哪吒变成了一个走私客
Where the water supply is controlled by a wealthy mafia family
生活在一个水源被黑帮控制的城市里
"It shouldn't be like this"
“不应该这样”
"But it's always like this"
“但一直都是这样”
One day, while protecting his sister from the mafia
有一天，被黑帮追杀的时候
Nezha's inner power awakens
哪吒的潜能被激发
He can now use his power to fight back
虽然有了反击的力量
But each time he does
可是每次反击
The mafia crushes down harder
黑帮就打压得更厉害
And everyone is hurt in the crossfire
交战之中，受伤的都是旁人
In its most basic form
《重生》的剧情安排
Nezha Reborn follows the original story plot point by plot point
与原故事大致相同
But cleverly updates the criticism from about the feudal system
但主题从批判封建制度
To wealth disparity
变成了贫富分化
A hot-pressed issue around the world today
也是时下最受关注的话题之一
See, in the original story
看原著中
The people Nezha helped, including Nezha himself Were children
哪吒帮助的人，包括哪吒本人都是孩子
The most helpless people in society
社会上最无助的人
And everyone who sided with the oppressor
站在压迫者一方的
Are officials and nobles
都是达官贵人
That includes Nezha's father, who's a general
这也包括哪吒的父亲，是个总兵
Whereas in Reborn
《重生》里
The dynamic has shifted
这个设定就有所改变
The victims of the conflict are, across the board, poor
受害者几乎全都是穷人
Nezha is no longer a child of a noble
哪吒也不再是官家之子
But a smuggler from a poor family
而是贫困家出的走私客
Cleverly, the film changes  Nezha's brother into a police officer
该片中，哪吒的哥哥变成了一名警察
"The bureau busted another smuggling case"
“缉私局刚又破了一个走私案子”
A police who deals with smugglers like Nezha
但只能对付哪吒这样的走私客
But has no power over the robberies and murders committed by the mafia
黑帮放火杀人，警察管不了
Every villain is either rich
每个反派要不有钱
Or greedy
要不贪钱
The law only exists to control the poor
法律只能用来管理穷人
In other words
换句话说
Even though the story looks different
即使故事看起来不同
Even though the angle has changed
即使主题的角度有所变化
The core of the message remains:
其核心问题依然不变
Is social inequality part of the natural order?
社会的不平等是自然而然吗？
Is violence against the oppressor necessary?
暴力是对压迫者的唯一反抗手段吗？
Is it acceptable to fight back
如果无辜的人会受伤
If it means innocent people will get hurt?
反抗是否还是正义？
The Chinese audience has no problem recognizing it as Chinese
中国观众一眼就能看出这部片的中国要素
Because it preserved the heart of Nezha
因为这当中保存了哪吒的中心思想
An influential folktale that defined what Chinese culture is
保存了中国文化重要的一部分
It is a Chinese story
这是一个中国故事
With an anime coat of paint
只是披着日式动漫的外衣
[Sponsored Message]
[赞助消息]
If today's video makes  you want to get into Chinese mythology
如果本期节目提起了你对中国神话的兴趣
The best way to start is how I started:
最佳入门作品当然就是
With Journey to the West
《西游记》啦
Which, you can find on Audible
在Audible上就能找到哦！
Crazy, right?
厉害了吧
Shouldn't be that surprising, though
不过也不是什么惊奇之事啦
The selection of audiobooks on Audible is pretty staggering
Audible上的有声读物数量真的很惊人
Anything from foreign classics
从汉语经典
To brand new releases
到最新书籍都有
Full transparency
老实说
I never actually finished Journey to the West
《西游记》我还真没读完
But now, I can enjoy the whole thing while cooking
但现在，我可以一边做饭一边享受故事啦！
As an Audible member, you get 1 credit every month
Audible会员每个月还能赚取分数
You can use it towards any title in the premium selection
换取会员区任何书本
And once you got them
一旦入手
You can keep them forever
终身拥有！
Visit audible.com/accented
现在登陆audible.com/accented
Or text accented to 500 500
或发送“accented”至500 500
And start your 30 days free trial today
马上开始30天免费试用
Whether you want to expand your horizon
无论是想开拓视野
Or have something to entertain you during transit
还是上下班期间找点娱乐
Sci-fi, Thriller, Romance, Comedy
科幻、惊悚、浪漫、搞笑
Audible is your one-stop shop
Audible都能为你提供
Go to audible.com/accented
登陆audible.com/accented
And try it out for free today
开始免费试用吧
[Chapter Two]
[第二章]
With the spirit of the story preserved
故事中心思想得以保存
Nezha Reborn can build its visual on top of a 500-year-old solid foundation
《哪吒重生》便在这个500年屹立不倒的地基上建造自己
But not without a lot of thoughts
但建造过程也是很讲究
One common criticism I heard about League of Gods
《封神传奇》的一大吐槽点
Is its incoherent visual style
就是他杂乱无章的视觉风格
It combines styles from European high fantasy
结合了欧洲奇幻电影风
With Mesopotamian structures
美索不达米亚的建筑风
And glazes it with copious amounts of gold
上边还涂了一层又一层的塑料金
No, we are not doing that
（你别闹）
Aside from the fact that nothing looks Chinese
看起来没有中国风就算了
(Which shouldn't really matter)
（反正也不重要）
(Not everything from China has to look Chinese)
（不是所有中国电影都要中国风）
How do these visual elements serve the story?
这些视觉元素是怎样联系到故事上的呢？
See, when Tolkien wrote The Lord of the Rings
看，当托尔金写《指环王》时
He infused it with his experience as a WWI soldier
他把自己在一战战场上的经历都写进去了
From the Battle of the Somme
从索姆河战役
To a world in decline
到世界衰落的悲观感
To Frodo's inability to return to his old life
再到佛罗多无法回家的结尾
When The Lord of the Rings references something
当《指环王》引用事情时
It doesn't just reference the visual
它不仅仅引用了视觉效果
But also the history
背后的历史
The culture
文化
And the emotion behind it
和情感也一并引用
At first glance
乍看之下
Reborn may look like Final Fantasy VII meets Akira
《重生》看起来像《最终幻想VII》加《阿基拉》
But quickly
但很快
The film reveals its root visual inspiration:
电影展示出它视觉灵感的根源
Republic Era China
民国时代中国
With its updated story
在这个新的演绎里
Reborn is essentially a gangster flick
《重生》其实就是一部黑帮电影
Not too dissimilar to classics like Scarface
与《疤面人》等经典电影统一范畴
The 1932 original, not the remake
注意我们说的是1932年原版，不是新版
It's a genre of film most commonly associated with the 1920s
这种电影常与1920年代联系在一起
Both in America, mostly Chicago
无论是美国的芝加哥
And in China, mostly Shanghai
还是中国的上海
To Chinese people
对中国人来说
Republic Era Shanghai is a paradox
民国上海让人百感交集
It's often depicted with nostalgia
戏剧中，上海充满怀旧感
A place of glamourous high fashion
是一个雍容华贵的地方
Yet, it is also remembered as a crime-ridden place
但又经常被描绘成一个犯罪天堂
Where the mafia ruled the streets
黑帮街头滥杀，无法无天
Where wealth disparity went out of control
贫富悬殊彻底失控的城市
It's remembered as a place divided up by colonizers
它是一个被殖民者瓜分的地方
It's remembered as a place where war looms over
它是一个战争迫在眉睫的地方
None of what I said is 100% historically accurate
当然这些都并不完全符合史诗
But that doesn't matter
但这并不重要
Because to a general audience
重要的不是史诗
Shanghai was PERCEIVED that way
而是观众的印象
And so, when Nezha Reborn takes on that aesthetic
所以，当《哪吒重生》选择使用民国美术的时候
It also takes on that perception through association
它也引用了背后的印象
Crime
犯罪
Social inequality
阶级分化
War
战争
This aesthetic is reinforced at every corner
这种印象在每个角落都表现得淋漓尽致
Nezha's brother looks exactly like a Republic Era cliche
哪吒的哥哥完全就是民国剧的刻板角色
The mafia is exactly how you remember it from Kung Fu Hustle
黑帮成员与《功夫》的斧头帮一个模版
Even the text is written right to left
连招牌都是从右到左
With era-appropriate fonts and styles
字体和设计也都符合那个年代
The details reinforce the sense of history and culture
细节巩固了印象背后的历史和文化
This history and culture, in turn, anchor the world
而这浓厚的历史和文化感则巩固了世界观
Allowing the audience to relate to and feel the movie
丰富了观众对世界的体验
It's only when all of that groundworks are done
只有基础牢固了
That Nezha Reborn can build the rest of its visual identity
《哪吒重生》才可以打造出
On top of this solid foundation
别样的视觉设计
The steampunk technology
不管是蒸汽朋克
The fashion
还是服装
The architecture
还是建筑
The less critical something is to the plot
越是和剧情不相关的内容
The more liberty can be taken
越是可以改编
Nezha's spirit?
哪吒的元神
Highly important
非常重要
Pretty traditional looking
看起来就很传统
A character referencing the Monkey King?
一个模仿孙悟空的角色
The association is strengthened
其住处设计
Through a related reference to his iconic Water Curtain Cave
引用了水帘洞的设计
The motorcycle?
哪吒的摩托车
Barely a set dressing
基本没有剧情
Historical accuracy can take a backseat
时尚一点也没关系
This is how you reimagine an old story
这就是改编老故事的方法
Keep the core of the story
保持故事核心
Explore it from a different angle
改编探索角度
Build a solid foundation through cultural and historical reference
通过参考文化和历史，建立坚实的基础
And only add a sense of style as the icing on top
而独特的视觉色剂，只是锦上添花的小部分
While it's often the outside appearance that gets praised
虽然观众喜欢称赞最亮眼的外表
Cliché as it may sound
但老套地说
It's always what's inside that matters
还是内在最重要啊
[Conclusion]
[结论]
I refrained from going very in-depth in this video
本期视频没有深入探讨剧情
Because I don't want to spoil this movie
因为我实在不想剧透
With all the context provided
看到这里
I think you can now enjoy the film to its fullest
就算你不熟悉中国神话
Even if you are unfamiliar with Chinese mythology
这部电影也应该能看懂了
But before we go
但结束之前
I'd like to take a little bit more time to just admire this movie
我想再花一点时间来欣赏这部电影
There is a reason I brought up the 1979 Nezha animation
本期视频提及1979年动画版哪吒，其实是有原因的
Well, aside from it being what many people consider to be
并不只是因为它是众多国人心目中
The definitive adaptation
的最经典
There is this one sequence
该动画中有这一幕
In which Nezha's father, with a sword in hand
哪吒的父亲手提着剑
Threatens to kill Nezha To restore order
说要杀了哪吒
And to appease the gods
顺天意而行
It was a perplexing scene for a lot of children
对很多孩子来说，这一幕让人难以理解
To me, and to everyone
因为大家都觉得
Nezha did the right thing
哪吒确实没做错
He's helping the weak
他确实是在帮助弱者
He's saving the people
他在救人
But at the same time
但同时
Nezha is undeniably violent
哪吒的暴力行为也不可否认
Is pulling out his god d#mn spine really necessary?
杀龙就算了，抽掉龙筋真的有必要吗？
The film manages to teach children
这部电影让孩子们意识到
The moral complexity in the adult world
成人世界的道德有多复杂
This shocking moment
这一幕
Is one of the most remembered images in Chinese animation history
是中国动画史上最令人难忘的画面之一
Nezha's death
哪吒之死
Makes us feel like something is unjust about the world
让我们感受到了世界的不公
A feeling that has only gotten more intense as we grow up
而这种感受，随着年龄的增长，慢慢变强
In Nezha Reborn
《哪吒重生》里
The morality behind Nezha's violence is even more ambiguous
哪吒的道德观则更加模糊
After the mafia robbery
逃避黑帮追杀时
Nezha's little sister lost a leg in the crossfire
哪吒妹妹在交火中失去了一条腿
Seeing this Nezha's first reaction isn't to stay by her side
面对这一幕，哪吒第一反应不是留在她身边
But to seek revenge
而是想报仇
And so
所以
When the villains accuse Nezha of being a violent, destructive person
哪吒被反派指责为一个喜欢暴力的灾星
Imagine my shock
这时候
When the movie shows me a scene
电影居然重现了
That directly referenced the 1979 classic
1979年动画的经典一幕
Faithfully recreated every single memorable image
忠实地再现了每一个令人难忘的画面
Somehow
我也不知道电影时怎么做到的
The movie makes me feel like I'm watching the animation
我再次感受到了第一次看哪吒动画时的感觉
I'm faced with the same morality question
我再次面对同样的道德问题
But now, with even more complexity
只是问题变得更加复杂
And I have to answer it as an adult
我也要用成人的身份来回答问题
Sadly, the film is not entirely successful
可惜的是，电影并不完全成功
The pace of the plot can be pretty messy
电影节奏有点凌乱拖拉
Scene to scene transitions are sometimes jarring
场景到场景的过渡经常不自然
It's almost like parts of the movie are cut out or unfinished
仿佛有片段被剪
Its own answer to the question  of violence and justice
电影对暴力和正义的讨论
Is also not entirely satisfying
也不完全令人满意
The movie isn't as philosophical  as everyone have hoped
这部电影没有达到大家期望的哲学高度
While these criticisms are certainly valid
这些批评都很有道理
There is a silver lining
但也不失为一件好事
We are now at a point where merely "good" is not good enough
中国动画已经发展到
Chinese animation has gotten to a point
普通的“好”动画已经不够好了
Where the audience has expectations
动画观众对作品有了要求
High expectations
有高的期望
In the past, I recommended Chinese animated films
过去，我推荐中国动画电影
With the premise that it's good for a Chinese production
前提往往都是“中国动画的优秀作品”
But, with this one...
但是，《哪吒重生》嘛
This might be it
我觉得
Chinese or not
放在中国以外
This is just... good
也是一部好作品
You should watch it
大家都应该看看